(SHARP BREATHS)
WOMAN: ♪ Having been eye
And ear witnesses ♪
♪ To all that our Mother
Has done ♪
♪ From the first time
She opened the Gospel ♪
♪ Till she sung
Her final song ♪
♪ It seems only good
To answer ♪
♪ The request
Of our brethren and sisters ♪
♪ Make a faithful record ♪
♪ Of Mother Ann Lee ♪
♪ The woman
Clothed by the sun ♪
As one might expect
of a miraculous person,
Ann Lee was born
on the 29th of February
in the year 1736.
-(SHEEP BLEATING)
-(BELLS TOLLING)
(CHICKENS CLUCKING)
MARY (VO): The second eldest
of eight children,
she was the daughter
of a blacksmith and his wife,
residing upon Toad Lane.
Situated beneath the looming
shadow of Christ Church,
Manchester's utmost feared
and favored place
of Christian worship.
Hurry now, William, or they
mightn't find a space for us.
MARY (VO): Wherever she went,
William followed his sister,
adoringly.
As William learned
to keep pace,
Ann and the boy's march
were to be in lockstep.
Again, like this, brother.
(BABY COOING)
(BABY BABBLING)
Bless this food, dear Lord.
We thank you.
-Amen.
(MOTHER HUMMING MELODY)
MARY (VO):
When Ann was a child,
her mind was taken up
with the things of God,
so that she saw
heavenly visions
instead of trifling toys.
(BELL TOLLING)
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
Hurry, William.
The coldly intellectual
Church of England
is more concerned
with ritual and power
than the plight
of the common people
who are at mercy of brutal laws.
A ten-year-old child
can be sentenced to death!
To death!
MARY (VO): Ann had great light
and conviction
concerning the sinfulness
and depravity of human nature.
She put her hands to work
and her heart to God,
laboring tirelessly
without complaint.
-Ann?
-A place for everything,
and everything in its place,
William.
(CHILDREN COUGHING)
WOMAN (VO) : George Whitefield
persistently preached
his sermons
from the steps
of Christ Church.
Ann yearned to dedicate herself
to serving God
with equal fervor.
GEORGE: ...preach the Gospel
to arouse the workers
to awareness of their rights!
WOMAN: What do you
call yourselves?
Because we conduct our worship
by "rule and method,"
some do refer to us
as Methodist.
-(FATHER GRUNTING)
-(BED CREAKING)
MOTHER: Shh!
The children can hear you.
MARY (VO): Ann's hatred
of "fleshly cohabitation"
dated from her earliest youth.
(GRUNTING CONTINUES)
MOTHER: Ann, what has
possessed you this morning?
You--
Speak intelligibly, Ann Lee.
I know what you do to her.
She doesn't mean anything
by it, sweetheart.
Hands on the table.
Flat on the table.
-(SWITCH STRIKING)
-(DOG BARKING)
(BABY CRYING)
MOTHER: Enough.
-(STRIKING CONTINUES)
-(GASPS IN PAIN)
That's enough now.
(STRIKING CONTINUES)
(WOMAN SCREAMING)
(RHYTHMIC CHANTING)
(OVERLAPPING WAILING)
(ROOSTER CROWING)
(SNORING)
I don't have to be
down the mills yet, do I?
(ANN SHUSHING)
It's not light yet.
I want to visit
my mother's resting place
on the way to the infirmary.
Uncle William will walk with you
to the mill this morning.
And Nancy,
if Uncle William's slow to rise,
clutch him by the nose.
Blame it on Auntie Ann.
(ROOSTER CROWING)
(GOATS BLEATING)
(BELL TOLLING)
(VILLAGERS CHATTERING)
MARY (VO): To be free
of the mill's wearying labor,
Ann found herself in service as
a cook at the local infirmary.
In the scant leisure
she possessed,
she yearned to find purpose
amidst the dullness of her lot.
(MAN COUGHING)
WOMAN: No! No!
(WOMAN SCREAMING)
(OVERLAPPING SHOUTING)
Pardon me.
The invalids
are having something
of a collective episode,
Miss Ann.
My companions
are waiting for me.
WILLIAM: Make haste, sister.
The assembly mightn't
welcome dalliers.
When have you known me
to dally, William?
There was some gruesome
commotion at hospital.
Gruesome?
Was someone injured?
A patient, self-harmed.
They barred the exits
of all faculty
until the coroner arrived.
Here, quickly.
Provisions from the kitchen.
Nicked an egg for each of you,
and some bread.
-Nicked?
-No, dear.
-I just saved it from waste.
-WILLIAM: Let's take our supper
as we tram over mountain
and moorland.
-(COWS LOWING)
-(SHEEP BLEATING)
No time to wash up, Nancy?
No, Auntie.
MARY (VO): Always seeking
a more harmonious consonance
between her faith in God
and the religious
establishment,
she attended a series
of local revival meetings
hosted by Jane
and James Wardley.
Good evening.
I would be remiss
if I were first
not to thank Mr. John Townley
for hosting us
in his beautiful home.
For those new here tonight,
perhaps you're unaccustomed
to hearing the voice
and seeing the demeanor
of a woman preacher.
So James and I thought
you might find this passage
particularly illuminating.
From Jeremiah...
"How long wilt thou go about,
O you backsliding daughter?
For the Lord hath created
a new thing on earth,
a woman shall compass a man..."
Christ's spirit first appeared
in the form of a man, Jesus,
but will eventually reappear,
to fulfill the promise
of the second coming,
in the form of a woman.
As we were all created
in his likeness,
God must be both
male and female.
WOMAN: Yes!
You there,
we have not seen you before.
May I ask,
what's drawn you to us?
I am Ann Lee.
This is my brother, William Lee,
and my late sister's daughter,
Nancy Lee.
Yes?
We've come because--
"For he who confesses,
shams are over
and realities have begun;
he has exteriorized
his rottenness."
Tell us why you've come.
Bare yourself to us.
Well...
many times
when I'm about my work,
I feel my soul overwhelmed
with sorrow.
I will work as long as I can
to keep it concealed
and then I will run
to get out of sight,
lest someone should pity me
with that pity
that God does not.
Welcome to the Wardley Society,
Ann, William, and Nancy.
Yes, welcome.
I'm Father James Wardley
and this is my wife,
Mother Jane.
When you confess your sins,
you must labor to remember
the time when and the place
where you committed them.
And when you have
confessed them,
you will cry to God
to know if your confession
is accepted.
And by crying to God,
you will eventually travel
out of your loss.
James Whittaker, please rise...
and share with us
your unflinching testimony.
Go on, James.
Give your grief to God.
Some years ago, I have by chance
seen my sister bathing and,
at once,
I was filled with a tremor
throughout my whole being.
My body quaked
at the sight of her
like a split peach.
It is improper
because she is a child.
It is wrong because she is
my own flesh and blood.
(REPEATEDLY EXHALING SHARPLY)
(WHITTAKER WAILING)
(WOMAN WAILING LOUDLY)
(WHITAKER GRUNTING RHYTHMICALLY)
(WOMAN CONTINUES WAILING)
MARY (VO): The Wardleys
had been devout Quakers,
dedicated to the belief
that true religion
comes from inward experience.
(WOMAN WAILING WILDLY)
(WHITTAKER SHOUTING)
MARY (VO): But had left
to form their own,
more dynamic,
religious community.
(WOMAN SHRIEKING)
They were known
as the Shaking Quakers,
or Shakers,
as the locals referred to them,
because of the shaking
and dancing
that characterized
their worship.
(BOTH CONTINUE WAILING)
(ALL GASPING IN RHYTHM)
(WOMAN SPEAKING IN TONGUES)
(WOMAN SHRIEKS AND LAUGHS)
(RHYTHMIC CHANTING
BREATHS CONTINUE AND FADE)
MARY (VO): Ann Lee had at last
discovered a community
that espoused her beliefs,
and she, in turn,
embraced their principles
wholeheartedly.
♪ La-la-la-la-la-la
La, la-la-la ♪
♪ La, la-la-la-la-la, la-la ♪
♪ La-la-la-la-la-la
La, la-la ♪
♪ La-la-la-la-la-la ♪
(VOCALIZING CONTINUES)
MARY (VO): There, she caught
the eye of a man
of the same faith,
Abraham,
a blacksmith like her father.
(VOCALIZING CONTINUES)
(HAMMERS CLANGING)
(WOMEN SHRIEKING)
(WOMAN GRUNTING)
(WOMAN SHRIEKING)
(VOCALIZING CONTINUES)
(WOMAN WAILING)
(MAN WAILING)
MARY (VO): She later
married Abraham.
Mary Partington bore witness
to the marriage ceremony,
but would ultimately
prove more true to Ann
than Abraham's solemn vow.
(VOCALIZING CONTINUES)
(ALL SHOUT)
(HOOVES CLATTERING OUTSIDE)
(FIRE CRACKLING SOFTLY)
I, uh... seized a copy
of this puzzling,
frequently concerning text,
off the person
of my new apprentice.
Now, it's filled
with terrible images,
but I find it has
some philosophical value,
as it's a direct
and unrelenting attack
on the traditional clergy.
That's atypical of literature
of this kind.
Who is its scribe?
Anonymous, far as I know.
What is it?
Well, from what I can tell,
it's the story of a young girl,
Thérèse,
facing a religious institution
rife with corruption.
Now, in the only segment
I've read,
Thérèse is hidden in a cupboard
as she watches
a fellow novice, Eradice,
instructed in the ways of prayer
by Father Dirrag, her confessor.
Why is Thérèse in a cupboard?
That is irrelevant.
May I go on?
So, he explains that Eradice
has been chosen by God
to experience his full presence.
Now, he then goes on to request
that she lift her skirt.
He then applies "the rope
of Saint Francis" to the nun,
causing her to feel
all the ecstasy
of an exalted
religious experience.
You've discovered this
on the person
of your new apprentice?
That is correct.
"And there appeared
a great wonder in Heaven,
a woman clothed with the sun,
the moon under her feet...
and a crown of twelve stars
upon her head.
She was pregnant.
She cried out in pain
as she was about to give birth."
Revelation 12:1.
-Take me in your mouth.
-No.
Open your legs.
(PANTING SOFTLY)
(PAINED GRUNT)
-(ABRAHAM GRUNTING)
-(SNAKE HISSING)
(PANTING)
(ANN SCREAMING)
(BABY CRYING)
(ANN PANTING HEAVILY)
Oh, he's beautiful.
-(BABY FUSSING)
-(SHUSHING)
MARY (VO): She went on
to give birth to four children.
But all died
before turning one.
(ANN VOCALIZING)
Come on.
(ANN SHUSHING)
(ANN VOCALIZING)
(BREATHES SHAKILY)
(VOCALIZING CONTINUES)
(PANTS RHYTHMICALLY)
(PAINED GASP)
(WOMEN VOCALIZING)
(ANN GROANING LOUDLY)
(GASPING)
(GASPING BREATHS)
♪ O the beautiful treasures ♪
♪ Laid up for the wise ♪
♪ O how precious the values ♪
♪ How glorious the prize ♪
♪ Far brighter than diamonds ♪
♪ On princes' brow ♪
♪ And richer than royalty ♪
♪ Can bestow ♪
♪ Beautiful treasures ♪
-♪ Beautiful treasures ♪
-(SCREAMING)
♪ Beautiful treasures ♪
(WOMEN WAILING)
♪ Far brighter than diamonds ♪
♪ On princes' brow ♪
♪ And richer than royalty ♪
♪ Can bestow ♪
♪ Far brighter than diamonds
On princes' brow ♪
-I have to take her now.
-(SOBBING) No!
-No!
-♪ And richer than royalty ♪
♪ Can bestow ♪
Ann! Ann! Ann!
We need to stop the bleeding.
Get help!
God. God, give me the strength
to go on.
God, give me
the strength to go on.
God, give me the strength
to go on.
MARY (VO): After the death
of her last child,
she was admitted
to the infirmary
where she'd once worked
as a cook.
(WIND BLOWING)
(HOOVES CLATTERING)
(WOMAN COUGHING)
Ann.
Mother Jane,
sometimes I go to bed and sleep,
but in the morning I cannot feel
that sense of the word of God
which I felt before I slept.
This brings me
great tribulation.
And then I cry to God,
and promise him,
that if he gave me
the same sense
I had before I slept,
I would labor all night again.
This I do night after night.
I see.
Our unbearable tragedies
are God's judgement upon me.
I sinned by permitting
my father and Abraham
to persuade me to forsake
my true feelings and marry.
Marriage, Ann, is not a sin.
I have fallen under heavy
trials and tribulations
on account of lodging
with my husband.
It is sexual sin that has
caused us to catastrophe.
I know it.
James and I lodge together,
but we do not touch each other
any more than two babes.
You may return and do likewise.
I will have James speak
with Abraham.
Come back to us, dear Ann.
You're not only a pillar
of our community,
but a leader, as well.
(INHALES DEEPLY)
MARY (VO):
With nothing left to lose,
Ann boldly converted
her suffering into evangelism.
Brothers!
(ALL CHANTING RHYTHMICALLY)
MARY (VO): Over the course
of three days,
she led the Shakers
in fervent worship.
(CHANTING CONTINUES)
(ANN WAILING LOUDLY)
Brothers!
Sisters!
MARY (VO): The power
of Ann's testimony
stirred up the rage
and enmity
of professor and profane
to such a degree
that her very life
and existence
seemed in continual jeopardy.
(WOMAN WAILING)
♪ I never did believe ♪
♪ That I ever could be saved ♪
♪ Without giving all ♪
♪ To God ♪
ALL: ♪ I never did believe ♪
♪ That I ever could be saved ♪
♪ Without giving all ♪
♪ To God ♪
♪ I never ♪
♪ Did believe ♪
BOTH: ♪ That I ever
Will be saved ♪
♪ Without giving all ♪
♪ To God ♪
MARY (VO): After three days,
having received
numerous complaints,
the local municipality
had quite enough
of the noisemaking.
ANN: "...but also Heaven,
so that the fishes of the sea
and the beasts of the fields
and all creeping things
that creep upon the earth
and to all men
upon the face of the earth
shall shake in my presence."
Welcome.
(ANN YELLING)
(ALL SHOUTING)
-(DOOR LOCKS)
-(KEYS JANGLING)
♪ I never ♪
♪ Did believe ♪
♪ That I ever could be saved ♪
♪ Without giving all ♪
♪ To God ♪
♪ So I freely give
The whole... ♪
MAN: That's enough!
♪ ...of my body ♪
♪ And my soul ♪
♪ To the Lord God ♪
♪ Amen ♪
(PANTING)
MAN: Anna!
(PEOPLE SHOUTING
INDISTINCTLY)
MAN: Anna!
Sister!
We've brought provisions
for you!
(FAINT CLAMORING OUTSIDE)
NANCY: Ann?
WILLIAM: Ann?
ANN: Brother William.
WHITTAKER: We're all here.
Can you hear my voice, Sister?
Is Abraham among you?
Circumstances would not
permit him
to depart his
dutiful obligations.
Alas, leave me now to pray.
But we've bread and wine, Ann!
All right, everyone.
You heard her.
(BELL TOLLING)
MARY (VO): This is
what happened to Ann Lee
whilst she was in prison.
-(FOOTSTEPS APPROACHING)
-(KEYS JINGLING)
In fastings, tears,
and incessant cries to God,
Ann bore such deep suffering
that her earthly tabernacle
was reduced until she was
as weak as an infant.
(DOOR CLANGING)
(BREATHING SHAKILY)
(BREATHING INTENSIFIES)
(BREATHLESS)
I hunger and thirst.
MARY (VO): Once more she cried
mightily to God for help.
(SNAKE HISSING)
God help me. God help me.
MARY (VO): This time,
her prayers were answered
by a blinding apparition.
The most astonishing visions
and divine manifestations
were presented to her in
so clear and striking a manner
that the whole spiritual world
seemed displayed before her.
♪ I hunger and thirst ♪
♪ After true righteousness ♪
♪ In what I've obtained ♪
♪ Of what I obtain ♪
♪ My soul cannot rest ♪
♪ I hunger and thirst ♪
♪ After true righteousness ♪
♪ An ocean I see
Without bottom or shore ♪
♪ Feed me, I'm hungry ♪
♪ Enrich me, I'm poor ♪
♪ I cry unto God ♪
♪ I'll never cease ♪
♪ Till my soul's filled
with love ♪
♪ Love and sweet peace ♪
♪ I hunger and thirst ♪
♪ After true righteousness ♪
WOMAN: ♪ And thirst ♪
ANN AND CHORUS:
♪ I hunger and thirst ♪
♪ After true righteousness ♪
MARY (VO): And there appeared
a great wonder in Heaven,
a woman clothed with the sun
and the moon under her feet.
And upon her head,
a crown of twelve stars.
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
MAN: Please, sir,
I am aching with hungriness.
What have you done to her?
Oh, you're warm.
You're breathing.
Wake up, Sister. Hear my voice.
It's me, William.
Here, drink this.
You must cut your locks,
Brother.
I need to see the Wardleys
forthwith.
MAN: Get ready to forgive
your sisters and brothers
on the first intonations
of repentance.
I was covered in a downy hair,
which I shed as I was reborn
into the most
astonishing visions,
and divine manifestations
that were presented to me
in so clear and striking
a manner,
that the whole spiritual world
was displayed before me.
And in
that soul-splitting moment,
I felt the cause
of all suffering and...
and the mystery of all evil,
revealed.
What did you see?
I... First I saw Adam and Eve
in the Garden of Eden.
I watched them defy God
and commit the forbidden
carnal act.
And then I witnessed
their expulsion from the garden
by an enraged deity.
And all at once, I understood
that there is one single cause
for humanity's separation
from God:
fornication.
ABRAHAM: Ann.
I, uh... I'm contrite
for coming only now.
The mill received
a hefty contract
for lattice fences, you see.
We've been inundated
with iron and steel
from the forge.
JANE: Ann Lee was relaying to us
that her earlier suspicions
have been confirmed.
She's discovered there is
only one way for humanity
to recover its lost state.
(RASPING COUGH)
JAMES: My understanding...
is to enter
a new age of spirituality,
men and women must abstain
from all lustful gratification
of the flesh.
Self-denial by celibacy
would be the first essential
for all men and women
who want to gain
the spiritual strength
to reach God.
Jane and I
are in agreement with you,
Mother Ann.
(SIGHS SOFTLY)
"Mother"?
WILLIAM: I love my Mother.
She is my sister,
but she has become my Mother.
And the Lord God made me
to love her.
(ANN PANTING)
During my period
of incarceration,
a sense of release
swept over me,
and my whole being
was suffused
with inner harmony and peace.
And I feel that all my sins
are now forgiven.
And that...
this is the vision
I shall carry in my heart
for the rest of my days.
Brother Abraham,
come and kneel
before our Mother Ann.
We'll have to say
our farewells tonight.
Been a great friend to me,
Jacob.
♪ So I freely give the whole ♪
♪ Of my body and... ♪
♪ And my soul ♪
♪ To the Lord, God ♪
♪ Amen ♪
MAN: God is faithful and just
to forgive us our sins
and to cleanse us
from all unrighteousness...
MARY (VO): And so,
they set forth with vigor
to enlighten all of Manchester
-that she, Ann...
-MAN: What is this?
MARY (VO):
Christ's Second Coming...
-was among them...
-What brings you to our doors?
and here
to liberate the community
from the moral failings
and oppressive doctrines
of the Church of England.
It is not I that speak.
-It is Christ who dwells in me.
-Blasphemy!
Get down from there
this very instant!
I have been in fine valleys
-with Christ as a lover.
-Blasphemy!
I am married
to the Lord Jesus Christ!
He is my head and my husband,
and I have no other!
-Get down from there!
-I have walked, hand in hand,
with God in Heaven.
Get down from there
this very instant!
You will hang for this,
young lady!
-It's blasphemy!
-WOMAN: Blasphemy!
(YELLS IN PAIN)
TIDESWELL: What is the woman
charged with?
-MAN: The charge is assault.
-WILLIAM: 'Tis a lie!
-My sister is a pacifist!
-MAN: And willfully
and contemptuously
disturbing divine service
-at Christ Church.
-JAMES: 'Tis a lie!
WOMAN: She claims herself wed
to the Lord Jesus Christ!
Quiet, now.
ANN: May I speak for myself,
Your Worship?
You may.
I live in celibacy,
and am wed to the Lord,
much like a nun
of your own church.
We have rejected
sinful pleasures of the flesh
and only share our love
with Jesus.
And Jesus spoke to me.
(SPEAKING LATIN)
MARY (VO):
According to one legend,
she spoke to them that night
in 12 languages,
including Greek, Latin,
Hebrew, and French.
By another account, she spoke
in 72 different tongues.
History states as a fact,
however,
that Mother Ann spoke
and manifested
such evident power of God
that the four ministers
of Christ Church
thought it only proper
to dismiss her.
Mother Ann,
I've posted your penalties.
You're free to go.
They are our penalties,
Mr. Townley.
It is our mission.
(OVERLAPPING SHOUTING)
This is beneath you!
Shame on you!
(PEOPLE CLAMORING)
Inventive in their reproach,
dear Brother.
MARY (VO): While some welcomed
the verdict with joy,
the thought of a woman preacher
infuriated others.
Do not run!
MAN: Shame on you!
WOMAN: You're a witch!
(WATER DRIPPING)
Thank you, Brother.
Where is your husband?
At the smithy,
morning and night.
Ah, yes.
Whenever my sister is imperiled,
Abraham finds himself
predisposed.
You must try and be
more understanding of him.
He's been through so much.
As have you.
Read me the morning paper,
will you?
There's something
on George Whitefield,
the man that used to preach
outside of Christ Church.
What's it say?
Read it aloud to me.
Courtesy of a raven messenger.
What am I looking at?
The piece
on Reverend George Whitefield.
The Methodist?
He has returned
from his fifth trip to America.
"With blazing eloquence,
Whitefield describes
opportunities for rebirth
of the spirit in America.
'The colonies,' he says,
'will one day
gain their independence,
and then freedom of conscience
will be secured
for all people to worship God
without hindrance or--'"
Am I to continue?
You don't grasp
its significance?
I have seen a chosen people
waiting for us in New England,
and I know that God wants us
to take the Millennial Church
to America.
And that he will aid us
in this enormous undertaking.
Are you mad?
Mr. Townley!
Father James,
you cannot possibly
expect me to foot this bill.
Nor to undertake such a journey
at my age.
My entire life,
not to mention my trade,
is here in Manchester.
I am unable to do our good work
amongst the Mancunian denizens
because their hearts and minds
are spoilt.
I cannot preach without
being harassed and assaulted.
Violated.
They will kill me, eventually.
Mother Ann, you have my utmost
respect and admiration--
Mr. Townley, it's not
the dying part which minds me.
I have lost
four beautiful children
with whom I anxiously wait
to be reunited.
It's the lost time.
Time to spread the word.
It is the lost voice
which minds me.
Thank you for your time
and generous access
to your home, Mr. Townley.
James--
Father James.
Look, my brother-in-law,
he's a farmer.
He's attended several
of our more sizable meetings
here at the house.
He's a shy man
and not a very polished
gentleman, perhaps,
but where there's muck,
there's brass, you see.
Yes?
Well, he has sometimes inquired
to me privately
as to how he might aid us
in our quest here.
Why have you never brought
this prospective sponsor
to our attention?
It seemed, at the time,
we had enough for our need.
Your brother-in-law
is John Hocknell.
JOHN: That's right.
You've spoken with him?
He approached Mother Jane and I
some time ago.
But we boasted then
of our loyalties to you.
Our quest is here no longer.
Mother Ann.
MARY (VO): It was decided
that James and Jane Wardley
should stay the course
in Manchester,
though their hearts ached
on the day
of their Mother Ann's
departure.
MARY (VO): Their berths
aboard the Mariah
were obtained at little cost,
the ship having been condemned.
Unsound in the eyes of men,
yet sufficient for those led
by the Spirit.
It set sail from Liverpool
on May 19th, 1774.
Their newfound patron,
John Hocknell's
means were modest,
but his devotion was boundless.
He'd have moved mountains
for Mother Ann,
let alone, moved house.
Without so much as a nudge,
Hocknell left everyone
and everything behind,
aside from
his know-nothing heir, Richard,
and his billfold.
(GOATS BLEATING)
(MAN COUGHING)
MARY (VO): Abraham never did
seem aught more
than a mere perplexed observer
of his wife's
theological virtues.
(MAN COUGHING)
He had, indeed,
been most uncertain regarding
the voyage to America,
yet was swayed
by the promise of innovation
in the working of metals
upon the shores of New York.
(BOAT HULL CREAKING)
(MAN COUGHING)
-Mother?
-Hmm?
There's something
I have been wanting to tell you.
Go on, Mary.
On our penultimate night
in Manchester,
following a 13-kilometer trek
on foot
from Brother Hocknell's farm
to transport his belongings
to the ports,
James Whittaker and I
were resting by the roadside
when a vision appeared to him.
Is that so?
He saw a large tree
"whose leaves," he said,
"shone with such a brightness
that made it appear
like a burning torch."
He took this to mean that he was
to help plant the tree of faith
in the New World.
We will plant a great big tree,
with deep and solid roots.
MARY: Mm.
Go to sleep now, Mary.
And I'll be sure Mr. Hocknell
never has you
carrying his bags again.
(MARY CHUCKLES SOFTLY)
NANCY: ♪ Today, today
Is my own time ♪
♪ Tomorrow can't be reckoned ♪
♪ And what is past
Cannot return ♪
♪ Though much to be regretted ♪
♪ Today, today is my own time ♪
♪ Tomorrow can't be reckoned ♪
♪ And what is past
Cannot return ♪
♪ Though much to be regretted ♪
BOTH: ♪ Then let me
Well improve each day ♪
♪ And lay me up a pleasure ♪
♪ Which will not rust
Nor wear away ♪
♪ But dwell with me forever ♪
MAN: Reef topsail!
MARY (VO): Mother Ann
led the group in daily worship
on the upper deck,
despite the vexation and grouse
of their fellow passengers
and crewmen.
Mother Ann, you must excuse me.
I feel quite ill again
this morning.
You're excused.
(RETCHING)
MARY: Four weeks, dear.
If the skies stay kind to us.
You must try
and keep some food down,
or you will only
become more feeble.
MAN: Take in fore topgallant!
♪ All is concert
All is summer ♪
-♪ All is concert ♪
-Still your bone box, besom!
-♪ All is summer ♪
-Shut it, he said.
-♪ All is concert ♪
-Hokum!
-♪ All is summer ♪
-Quiet down!
-Oi! Whooperups!
-♪ All is concert ♪
-♪ All is summer ♪
-Shut up!
-♪ All is concert ♪
-♪ All is summer ♪
-Shut up!
-Don't sing!
-♪ All is concert, all is-- ♪
My dear brethren
and sisters, stop!
(SINGING STOPS)
We must pray for the seafarers.
MAN: Shut your bone box, besom!
Impoverished souls!
Adventitious sinners!
These men know not
what they give tongue to.
I know just what I say, missus.
Shut it!
These men know not what they do.
-Stop!
-We must pray for them.
-♪ All is concert ♪
-Stop that!
-Shut it, he said!
-♪ All is summer... ♪
Shut up!
-Oi, whooperups! Quiet!
-♪ All is summer ♪
-Shut up!
-♪ All is concert ♪
(THUNDER BOOMING)
SMITH: Take in topgallant!
MAN: Take in topgallant!
SMITH: Take in royal!
(SHAKERS SINGING)
I am ordering all clamorous
and disruptive noisemaking
ceased without delay!
-Captain, stop!
-You heard me.
Halt where you are, Captain.
We are in various states
of undress!
If you do not stop the racket,
I have vowed my crewmen
to have all your disobedients
cast into the sea!
-And I am earnest.
-We do fear God
more than we fear Captain Smith
and we shall
conduct our worship, as usual,
with special orison
for seafaring sinners.
And you, Captain,
we shall pray for you, as well.
(LOUD CRASHING)
ANN: Mary, take my hand!
SMITH: (GRUNTS) Take refuge!
Sister Ann!
Do not exit your cabins
until you've received word
that it is safe to do so!
MAN: Prepare to set
storm canvas!
Lower broad sail!
Don't go up there, miss!
You'll be sucked out to sea.
The lot of you
should be pleased, then.
(SHIP RUMBLING, CREAKING)
(WOMAN WAILING)
(THUNDER RUMBLING)
Cunningham.
Captain!
SMITH: Prepare to cover
the hatches!
MAN: Preparing!
SMITH: A plank has been
struck loose at the keel.
I have gone upstairs
to look through the porthole
to the upper deck.
There is no way to mend it.
We must all perish
before morning.
Be of good cheer, Captain!
There shall not the hair
on our heads perish.
We will arrive safely
in America.
MARY (VO): Ann explained
that she had seen
two bright angels of God
standing by the mast,
through whom she received
the promise
of their safe-passing.
I will call now on my companions
to assist your crewmen.
MARY: Ann!
(HULL CREAKING)
(PEOPLE SHOUTING)
MARY (VO): Soon after,
a mighty wave struck the ship
and pressed
the loose plank tight,
stopping the leak.
Shakers fervently helped
the sailors at the pumps,
which, as the Captain noted,
had a miraculous effect.
(GROANING WITH EFFORT)
They were left to pray in peace
for the rest of the journey.
♪ High over the billows
We are wafted along ♪
♪ Angel wing carry us ♪
♪ Not one ripple
To break on our song ♪
♪ All is peace before us ♪
♪ All is concert,
All is summer ♪
♪ While to heaven
We are going ♪
♪ But in the desert
We are leaving behind ♪
♪ Wintry winds are blowing ♪
(MEN VOCALIZING)
♪ High over the billows
We are wafted along ♪
♪ Angel wing carry us ♪
♪ Not one ripple
To break on our song ♪
♪ All is peace before us ♪
♪ All is concert
All is summer ♪
♪ While to heaven
We are going ♪
♪ But in the desert
We are leaving behind ♪
♪ Wintry winds are blowing ♪
♪ All is concert
All is summer ♪
(THUNDER RUMBLING)
(PANTING DEEPLY)
(CATTLE LOWING)
(BELLS CLANGING)
(MEN SHOUTING)
(HORSE WHINNIES)
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
(WHISPERING)
Cunningham. Cunningham.
AUCTIONEER: I'm gonna start
the bidding at 150.
There's no need to waste time.
He's the pick of the herd,
gentlemen.
You won't find his like
-in these degenerate days.
-Are they selling them?
AUCTIONEER: Who'll give me 150?
Sinful as it is
incomprehensible.
-MAN: 160!
-AUCTIONEER: 170!
Every man, woman, and child
is a child of God.
MAN 2: 170.
Mother Ann, the women are tired.
Should I look into a bed stay
for the evening?
That's a terrible waste
of your resources, Mr. Hocknell.
Please hold on to your notecase.
-These men are without disease.
-Shame!
-JOHN: Shame!
-WILLIAM: Shame!
-Shame!
MARY (VO): On that hot
August afternoon,
the Shakers went in search
of a wide avenue
called Broad Street,
where Mother Ann felt confident
she would discover
what her vision had revealed.
Pardon me, are you the mistress
of this house?
WOMAN: I am.
Mrs. Cunningham?
You'll have to please excuse me,
I've just stepped outside
to escape the heat, you see.
Have we made acquaintance?
I am commissioned
by the Almighty God
to preach the everlasting gospel
to America.
And an angel commanded me,
here, to this house,
to make a home for me
and my people.
She said the name, Cunningham.
MARY (VO): Mrs. Cunningham was
a simple-minded woman
who recently faced
financial hardship...
I see.
...and began offering
affordable accommodations
in her home.
Although she didn't possess
deep faith,
she had a great curiosity
about the world.
She felt privileged
to have been chosen
by a higher force,
which motivated her
to provide discounted rates
along with a warm welcome
to her guests.
(INAUDIBLE CHATTER)
(SILVERWARE CLATTERING)
May I please be excused,
Mother Ann?
You may, Nancy.
Our privy is located just
outside across the vestibule.
You'll see a doorway
to exit through
at the far end
of the corridor.
Thank you kindly,
Mrs. Cunningham.
If you'll please excuse me,
as well.
I'll step out front
for some fresh air.
My equilibrium thinks me
still aboard the Mariah.
(LIGHT CHATTER, LAUGHTER)
(MOANING SOFTLY)
I haven't washed.
The night of the tempest,
I thought I mightn't ever
see you again.
We mustn't waste another moment.
We mustn't.
(BOTH GASP, PANTING)
The men among us shall stay
only a fortnight.
James Whittaker, William,
my son, Richard,
and I must leave,
in search of a suitable piece
of land up the Hudson
on which for us to settle.
Have you a boatman arranged
for your journey upriver?
JOHN: Is there someone
you might suggest?
I'm closely familiar
with a Dutchman, a hunter,
who's well acquainted
with those macabre customs
of the wild people.
Wild people?
River Injuns.
And to go from New York
to Albany,
you consult not a timetable
but a calendar.
So, in mild weather,
you take a boat,
but when the Hudson is frozen,
it's a stagecoach.
Either way,
it is a three-day trip.
And you, Standerin?
Will you be going along, too,
with the others?
I, uh, plan to stay behind,
seek work here in town,
aid in the support
of our mission.
JOHN: Accompany me
to the forge tomorrow.
We'll see if there are gaps
which need filling.
Abraham is a remarkable farrier.
JOHN: Where has that boy of mine
gone to?
Pardon me, will you?
Discourtesy is so unlike him.
Seems like his breadbasket
is all tied up in knots.
(LIGHT LAUGHTER)
JOHN: Richard!
-(RICHARD AND NANCY PANTING)
-(DISGUSTED GROAN)
God in Heaven!
(PANTING CONTINUES)
They are not willing to forsake.
They plan to marry.
Then they must leave us.
Is their love so sinful?
No, 'tis a thing of beauty.
They can love each other deeply,
like I love you.
They...
The love they have chosen
will not last.
It will turn your body into
a senseless, unsavory corpse.
(BREATHES SHAKILY)
The desire of the flesh
will fester and tear it apart.
And that desire is
an ugly beast.
And that beast destroys
all that is beautiful and pure.
Both of us have suffered
on our journey.
We have made
tremendous sacrifices
to receive the greatest love
that one can experience,
and to give it entirely.
It pains me to see her go.
I would force her to stay
and send him away.
She was left in our care,
after all.
But that we cannot, William.
She must choose
our way of life freely.
(ANN SNIFFLES)
(MEN AND WOMEN
VOCALIZING SOFTLY)
(ANN WHIMPERS LIGHTLY)
(DOOR THUDS GENTLY)
(HORSE NICKERING)
MARY (VO): Regretful
and ashamed,
Hocknell's son, Richard,
and Ann's niece, Nancy,
were exigently forced to leave
their family and friends behind
without pageantry of farewell.
-(WHIP SNAPS)
-(HORSE WHINNIES)
Eight became six.
(BIRDS CALLING IN DISTANCE)
Slept like wee babes,
did you, lads?
As well as one might on a raft.
Didn't Cunningham say
he was Dutch?
He's a Dutchman.
DUTCHMAN:
Beautiful morning now, I say.
But again,
all white geese are swans.
MARY (VO): To the great
frustration of the Irishman,
the men journeyed upstream
without a clear itinerary
or navigational aids,
relying solely
on Mr. Hocknell's instincts.
(BIRDS TWITTERING)
DUTCHMAN: It's been two days,
Mr. Hocknell.
Nothing seems to stir
your imagination.
JOHN: It is not me imagination.
It is me Divine inspiration
that is leading us.
MARY (VO): The night before
their expedition,
Brother Hocknell had shared
a vivid dream with the men,
featuring an expansive field
with tall grass,
bordered by 12 large oak trees.
They all believed
this was the ideal place
for them to settle.
These are the wild people
we have compensated you
to protect us from?
DUTCHMAN: The women
and children, yes.
The manful redskin, yet.
You've never lain your eye
on a more wretched brute.
(JOHN MUTTERING INDISTINCTLY)
Your friend's a bit mad, is he?
He doesn't help us to cook
or make camp.
I'm not mad,
but perhaps
I've become indolent
in my old age.
I'm not cheap, however,
so I've afforded myself
the opportunity to do nothing.
May I pray now to
the Almighty God in some peace?
I'm sorry, Lord,
I could not control my temper.
And it is something
I have been working on.
I should not have lashed out
at this common man
who does not understand
the path that we're on,
who cannot comprehend in any way
the kind of endurance
that is required
to make this journey.
I weakened at a point
when I should have been strong,
and I really beg you
for forgiveness.
And I will apologize
to this man,
although he does
get under my skin
with his pettiness
and his small-mindedness.
But I should rise above that.
I should know better.
I sit in endless gratitude
for all the gifts
that you've given me...
DUTCHMAN: Did you sleep a wink,
Mr. Hocknell?
...that you are constantly
bestowing upon me.
MARY (VO): Legend has it,
that on the third day
of the men's search,
a most peculiar thing happened.
Brother Hocknell?
♪ I am searching
I am led ♪
WILLIAM: ♪ He is searching
He is led ♪
JOHN: ♪ I am searching
I am led ♪
WILLIAM: ♪ He is searching
He is led ♪
JOHN: ♪ What eyes reveal ♪
♪ It's our ideal ♪
BOTH: ♪ That our ordeal
Is worth it ♪
♪ I am searching
I am led ♪
♪ He is searching
He is led ♪
♪ I am searching
I am led ♪
♪ He is searching
He is led ♪
JOHN: ♪ What eyes reveal ♪
♪ It's our ideal ♪
BOTH: ♪ That our ordeal
Is worth it ♪
DUTCHMAN: Brother Hocknell!
JOHN: ♪ What eyes reveal ♪
♪ It's our ideal ♪
♪ That our ordeal is worth it ♪
♪ Oh, God, I saw it ♪
♪ Like through a glass ♪
♪ My visions shall ♪
♪ Come to pass ♪
♪ Pass ♪
ALL: ♪ Pass ♪
(SIGHS DEEPLY)
(BIRDS TWITTERING)
(FOOTSTEPS)
(LIQUID SLOSHING)
(WHISPERS) Brother Abraham,
is something the matter?
ABRAHAM: I need to speak
with her in private.
-Brother?
-Sister, go and take my bed.
The men are away now.
Please, just leave me
in peace with her.
(FEET SHUFFLING)
(DOGS BARK IN DISTANCE)
-(ANN GASPS)
-Mother,
I've endured your sensual
abstinence for six years...
(WHISPERS) You are setting
a terrible precedent.
No, you will not
talk over me!
Quiet your voice!
(SIGHS)
I will give you a chance now
to rectify your standing
in my eyes.
Go to bed with me, dutifully,
as you once promised.
No one can reach God
while wallowing
in the lust of the flesh.
Oh, enough!
I want to please
my husband, I do.
But I cannot.
My natural instincts
have died away in love of God.
I urge you to renounce
your testimony...
and live in sexual cohabitation
like the rest of the world.
Abraham, the exuberant bliss
of Christ--
ABRAHAM:
No. And the more you talk of
"exuberant bliss
of Divine intercourse,"
the more I shall drink, and
not stop myself until I am dead.
-(DOGS BARKING)
-(WIND BLOWING)
Do those that follow thou
and abide ye's every locution,
know their Mother Ann
to be illiterate?
Tell me...
how does one contribute
to the scripture
if thou cannot stable a quill?
I've kept your secrets, Ann Lee.
And you will keep mine.
(FOOTSTEPS RECEDING)
(DOOR SHUTS)
(PANTING)
(DOOR THUDDING)
(FOOTSTEPS APPROACHING)
ABRAHAM:
So you are to be my wife now.
Go to the room. Now.
Now, if you do not consent
to sexual cohabitation with me,
I will take this woman
for my wife.
I will not do it,
if you should take my life
as consequence for my refusal.
(PANTING)
I'll do anything for my husband
which justice, reason,
and humanity requires,
but I do not consent
to violate my duty to God.
And I will endeavor
to prevail on you
to return to your duty
and be faithful.
(SHOUTING)
Don't! Be quiet!
-(SHOUTS)
-Shh.
I solemnly vow
I shan't utter another word
if you just lower your voice.
Lower your voice.
I will listen.
Shhhh.
(BOTH PANTING)
You have been paid.
You are to be my wife now.
Come. Good.
Now, take me in your mouth.
(GASPS)
Now you-you are my wife now.
Go on. There.
(PANTING)
MARY (VO): During
that long, bitter winter,
Mother Ann endured
deep sorrow of the soul.
Her children were dead.
Her husband had left her.
Her mission to America
seemed doomed.
(RHYTHMIC BREATHING)
But, with the arrival
of spring,
came news from the men
that it was time for
the women to journey upriver
and reunite
with their brothers.
JOHN: From here, as far
as the eye can see, Mother,
it is ours.
The deed is done.
Brother Hocknell...
Tell it, brother.
How is anyone meant to find us
camouflaged by the pines?
My dear children. Hold fast.
Be not discouraged.
God has not sent us
to this land in vain.
He sent us to bring the Gospel
to this nation,
which is deeply lost in sin.
And there are a great number
who will embrace it.
And the time draws nigh.
Do you truly believe the Gospel
will open to the world?
Yea, Brother William.
I certainly know it will.
And the time is near at hand
when they will come like doves.
Mother, you have often
told us so, but...
they do not come.
We are so few,
yet we have lost so many.
Brother William,
you will go out and preach
and make our presence known.
Be patient.
Be patient, my dear children.
For I have seen
a great number coming now.
And you will soon see them
coming in great numbers.
I know it.
MARY (VO):
After securing the land,
Brother Hocknell
had but enough capital left
to hire help to till it.
Yet Mother Ann
was eager to welcome
the farmers to the faith
and would not rest
until each one had joined.
MARY (VO): Soon thereafter,
Mother Ann sent Brother William
on a quest for new followers.
(BIRDS CALLING)
On the 19th of May,
in the year 1780,
the sky turned a strange hue.
William had heard tale
of a small godly lot,
who were certain
Judgment Day were nigh.
PASTOR: Let it touch
your skin like silk or fire.
Now, each and every thing shall
be raised to life before God.
May he be praised...
Fear not,
the day of Resurrection is here.
Look up to God
at the first rays of the sun.
Let it touch your skin
like silk or fire.
Look up! Look up! Look up!
Fear not!
(WOMEN SCREAMING)
PASTOR:
Now, here it is, without delay!
At last! At last! At last!
-(WOMEN SCREAMING)
-(CRYING)
-You lied to us.
-What does it mean, Father?
-(PEOPLE SHOUTING)
-Hold your words, please!
Everyone, hold your words.
There were countless signs!
All led here.
What have I missed?
(SLAPS BOOK ON TABLE)
Are my calculations mistaken?
Or perhaps the Lord
hath taken pity on us all.
Father, could it be that
the cataclysm of your sermon--
Make no words,
Deacon Talmadge Bishop.
I require consultation
from our neighboring parishes.
I must journey to them at once
and collect their insights.
Your neighboring ministers
are of ill repute, Father.
St. Paul says it is no sin
for women to speak in churches.
Though I remain dubious,
I am drawn to hear her speak.
All that I have told you
is true,
but I advise you
to go for yourself,
and speak to Mother Ann.
MARY (VO):
The news of religious liberty
stirred up many a sect
in America.
Most preaching doom
before paradise.
But Ann's word, paradise
through toil and chastity,
were a far simpler promise
to fulfill.
(RHYTHMIC BREATHING)
♪ Bow down, O Zion ♪
♪ And pray unto Heaven ♪
♪ That God in His mercy ♪
♪ Return unto thee ♪
CONGREGATION: ♪ For thee
For, for thee ♪
♪ For thee
We have labored for years
in the work of the regeneration,
and have risen with Christ.
We have traveled with him
in the resurrection.
-♪ That God in His mercy ♪
-For the light and power of God
was revealed to our Mother Ann,
and through her,
reveals to those
who receive her testimony.
Such sensible effect in
giving them power over all sin.
♪ For thee
For, for thee ♪
-♪ O, fall on the rock ♪
-ALL: ♪ Rock ♪
♪ Each one and be broken ♪
♪ Mother's devotion ♪
♪ To set us all free ♪
Revelations and gifts of God
that she was received
and acknowledged
-as the first spiritual leader!
-♪ Fall on the rock ♪
♪ Each one and be broken ♪
-♪ Mother's devotion ♪
-(WAILING)
♪ To set you all free ♪
We are located
just a mere ten miles north.
♪ Mother's devotion ♪
♪ To set us all free ♪
I will take you there myself,
personally.
♪ Mother's devotion ♪
♪ To set us all free ♪
CONGREGATION: ♪ For thee
For, for thee ♪
♪ Mother's devotion ♪
♪ To set us all free ♪
CONGREGATION: ♪ For thee
For, for thee ♪
ALL: ♪ Mother's devotion ♪
♪ To set us all free ♪
CONGREGATION: ♪ For thee
For, for thee ♪
(SCREAMING)
(THUMPING)
(PEOPLE VOCALIZING)
MARY (VO): The first winter
proved most trying.
As they broke the land,
the swamp yielded its serpents
and stinging pests.
(SINGING, HUMMING)
MARY (VO):
Soon, sickness spread.
(COUGHING)
MARY (VO):
And fever took hold.
(VOCALIZING CONTINUES)
MARY (VO): The Shakers kept
friendly with their neighbors,
knowing them to be skilled
in woodworking,
and willing to trade
teaching for goods.
-(CLAPPING)
-(VOCALIZING)
MARY (VO): "Do all your work
as though you had
a thousand years to live
and as you would if you knew
you must die tomorrow,"
-she would say.
-(ANN SCREAMING)
(PEOPLE HUMMING, SINGING)
MARY (VO):
Like all true leaders,
Mother Ann
never asked her people
to do anything
she would not do herself.
(VOCALIZING)
MARY (VO): The Shakers knew
that the best way to reach God
was by laboring tirelessly,
always striving for perfection.
With indefatigable faith,
they toiled side-by-side
to raise a lasting home.
Little mindful of the war
that raged about them.
(VOCALIZING CONTINUES)
MARY (VO): At last,
she had found
a sanctuary for her people.
For those new here,
who are unaccustomed
to a woman preacher.
WILLIAM:
"A woman shall compass a man."
Christ's spirit
first appeared as a man,
but has reappeared
to fulfill the promise
of the Second Coming as a woman.
Our Mother Ann.
And as we were all created
in His likeness, see,
God must be
both male and female.
For those wedded cohabitants
here today,
you must forsake
the marriage of the flesh
or you cannot
be married to the lamb.
We have had
the power of God upon us
and have felt great tribulation
for our sins.
After which we have felt
great love and releasement,
thought ourselves converted.
Is not this of Jesus Christ?
Yes, it is my brother
and husband.
It is us both, you see.
The gifts and calling of God
given to souls
in nature's darkness
not because they have repented,
but they are intended
to lead souls to repentance.
What is this repentance?
To leave off committing sin
is the only repentance
which God accepts.
Short of making an honest
and faithful confession
of all the sins ever committed
in your whole life.
It is God alone
that can forgive sins,
where then is the necessity
of confessing them to man?
WILLIAM: God has established
that order for all souls
who have committed sins that
they must confess their sins
before His chosen witnesses.
Do not be frightened, girl.
We do not bite.
Brother William tells me
you have borne seven children
yet at such a young age.
I have.
And did you receive them all
with equal joy?
(CLEARS THROAT)
No.
Is that so?
For she who confesses,
shams are over
and realities have begun.
She has exteriorized
her rottenness.
Routinely, see, when I went out
to fetch some water...
a terrible thought
might come on.
As I cradled our infant boy...
an overwhelming impulse
surged through me.
The desire to release him
into the depths of the well
and leave.
Seeking solace
from the undoubtedly
ceaseless wailing in the woods
behind the wash shed.
In that moment, the longing
for tranquility and silence
felt stronger
than the will to live.
-Give your grief to God.
-MAN: Your grief to God.
HOCKNELL:
Give your grief to God.
ANN: Give your grief to God.
(WOMAN WAILING, SINGING)
(RHYTHMIC BREATHING)
(WAILING)
(MOANS)
(RHYTHMIC GRUNTING, BREATHING)
(ANN SHOUTS)
ANN: More love, Brothers!
(ALL GRUNTING)
More love, Sisters!
-(GRUNTING)
-(WOMEN WAILING)
This is our altar,
and our altar is love!
None can build this altar
or sacrifice upon it
but the pure in heart,
and such are we!
We will sacrifice upon it!
-And we will love each other!
-(GRUNTING, WAILING CONTINUE)
(GRUNTING, WAILING)
MARY (VO): The trumpet
of Mother's everlasting gospel
began to sound.
And many flocked to Niskayuna
from various quarters.
Thus, the long expectations
of Ann Lee's church
were fully realized.
William, the Elder?
WILLIAM: Yes, Brother, it is I.
Have we made acquaintance?
-(INDISTINCT)
-(CHATTERING, LAUGHING)
This way, children.
Come with me.
HEADMASTER: Come along now.
A place for everything,
and everything
in its place, William.
WILLIAM:
There are so many children.
We have found that
a great many need caring for
and plenty who have none.
Some come
with their mothers alone,
some come
with their fathers as well.
All little ones are free of sin.
Later, they can choose for
themselves to stay pure or not.
So, tell us, Brother.
You have
our undivided attention.
(SIGHS)
The devil is a real being.
As real as a bear.
And I know, for I have seen him
and fought with him.
But I have encountered
and gathered
a many righteous
brother and sister also.
I have amassed a following
across towns near and far.
A community of persons who long
to be in the presence
of their Mother Ann.
ANN: We have made a great
advancement during your absence.
WILLIAM: That, I can see.
Imagine my delight
at this land tilled,
edifice erected, new faces
in every and all direction.
It is exactly
as you said it would be.
Mother, I've seen a vision.
A large, black cloud rising
as black as thunder.
A wartime is coming.
You are not wrong.
WILLIAM: On my travels,
I obtained a pamphlet
from a Mr. Valentine Rathbun,
Minister of the Gospel
which concerns me greatly.
-May I read from it, Mother?
-You may.
"To obtain instruction from
the woman preacher, Ann Lee,
I went to Niskayuna and gave her
a lengthy relation of my life.
In return, she made me
many wonderful promises.
Shakerism
is a religion of bluff,
and its adherents are fanatics.
I myself beheld the following,
and know, therefore,
whereof I speak.
They meet together
in the dead of night
and have been heard
two miles away by people.
They run about in the woods
and elsewhere,
hooting and tooting like owls
while some dance
and make such a bedlam as only
the insane can thrive upon."
Yes, he was here for the winter,
but he was not well-suited
for our community
and was asked to leave.
Brother William,
this is to be expected.
For we have long endured
such slanderous conceits.
This is different.
It goes on and on.
But hear this.
"Most of those who join
Ann Lee's movement
are urged to cry out against
the military defense
of the country,
against fighting
the common British foe.
Ann Lee's scheming religion
is not only treasonous,
it is also aimed at bre--
(GRUNTS)
It is also aimed at breaking up
life as we know it.
She causes
husbands and wives to part.
I am convinced the spirit which
prevails over this new scheme
is the spirit of witchcraft.
Ann Lee is Satan in the guise
of a sweet angel of light.
Some of the women Shakers
strip naked in the woods."
MARY: That is because the
brethren pulled off their coats
or outside garments, to labor,
or as the world
would call it "dance."
And in warm weather the sisters
being lightly clothed, but...
but they would report
we dance naked!
And you know how apt
the ignorant and vulgar parts
of mankind are
to misrepresent
what they see.
If one told we dance naked
with but few clothes on,
another in telling the story
would miss out that part.
It is not the baseless
accusation of vulgarities
which concerns me, Sister Mary.
For treason,
Mother could be jailed or worse.
ANN: Not long ago,
a general came along
with two magisterial gentlemen
on horseback,
declaring that they required
we take an oath of allegiance
to the country
and join them in the fight
for this nation's independence.
And what did you reply?
I merely explained that
the people of this community
will never do them any hurt,
for we are well-wishers
to the country.
And we will do all the good
to the country
that we are able to do.
Good.
That is good.
But I also made explicit
that we are unwilling
and unable to kill the devil
with the sword.
Hear me.
We must hide you, Mother.
William, sit down.
Do not be rash. Rest, please.
I need you to hear me.
They will return for you.
Rest, William.
All will be clear as
crystal glass on the morrow.
(PATSY HUMMING)
♪ Oh, my pretty Mother's home ♪
WOMAN: ♪ I love Mother ♪
-♪ Sweeter than the... ♪
-♪ I love her way ♪
♪ ...honey in a comb ♪
WOMAN: ♪ I love her gospel ♪
♪ Precepts to obey ♪
♪ Oh, my pretty Mother's home ♪
♪ I love Mother ♪
-♪ Sweeter than the... ♪
-♪ I love her way ♪
♪ ...honey in the comb ♪
-♪ Come love pretty love ♪
-♪ I love her gospel ♪
♪ Come, come, come ♪
-♪ Come love pretty love ♪
-♪ Precepts to obey ♪
♪ I want some ♪
♪ I love Mother ♪
♪ I love her way ♪
♪ I love her gospel ♪
♪ Precepts to obey ♪
♪ I love Mother ♪
♪ I love her way ♪
♪ I love her gospel ♪
♪ Precepts to obey ♪
I've added south facing
casements
for the dwelling houses.
And lintels
for on the surrounds.
Yeah, two on either side.
And rid it of
the gratuitous ornamentation.
♪ I love Mother
I love her way ♪
♪ I love her gospel ♪
♪ Precepts to obey ♪
♪ I love Mother ♪
♪ I love her way ♪
♪ I love her gospel ♪
♪ Precepts to obey ♪
It removes the skin, see?
An object from our Brothers
at the smithy's invention.
May I see Mother later, please?
Mother Ann will be here
for supper.
She meant our mother.
Sister Martha
will also be at supper.
♪ I love Mother ♪
♪ I love her way ♪
♪ I love her gospel ♪
♪ Precepts to obey ♪
♪ I love Mother ♪
♪ I love her way ♪
WILLIAM:
If you are ever to be saved,
it must be by walking
as He walked.
♪ I love Mother ♪
♪ I love her way ♪
♪ I love her gospel ♪
♪ Precepts to obey ♪
♪ I love Mother ♪
♪ I love her way ♪
♪ I love her gospel ♪
♪ Precepts to obey ♪
♪ The king may have
His throne ♪
♪ The miser his gold ♪
♪ The monarch his palace
And the princess her home ♪
♪ I covet none of theirs
For I've the gospel call ♪
♪ And a kind loving Mother
Which is better than them all ♪
♪ I love Mother ♪
♪ I love her way ♪
(HOOFSTEPS RUMBLING FAINTLY)
MARY (VO): A month later,
Mother Ann was taken away
just as Brother William
had predicted.
The Elder, James Whittaker,
traveled at once
to inform the Governor
of New York
about Mother Ann's
imprisonment, harsh treatment
and sufferings.
(BELL TOLLING)
The Governor, George Clinton,
pronounced disapproval
of jailing persons
for their pious beliefs.
And due to lack
of treasonable evidence,
he believed the woman
should be freed.
(BELL TOLLING)
(BIRDS CAWING)
(JOHN COUGHING)
Mother.
Rest, Brother.
(JOHN MOANING)
We've travelled day and night,
Brother Hocknell.
Mother is here now.
He's taken no food
for the last day.
We came as fast as we were able.
Rest, brother.
(JOHN GROANS)
(SIGHS) Last--
Last month, God's gift
cured me whooping cough,
but it remanifested as
these blisters on my hands
to signal that my work
here was not yet done.
He spoke to me and said,
"I have work for you to do,
and when your--
your work is done...
the same cough
will return to you
and take you out of this world."
So, we labored to finish the
second dwelling house, Mother.
The house is beautiful,
Brother John.
(BELL TOLLING)
(BELL TOLLING CONTINUES)
MARY (VO): Having again
lost six precious months
of her lifetime
to a term of incarceration,
she soon set forth
on a spiritual crusade
to spread the Gospel
throughout New England.
♪ How can I but love
My dear faithful children ♪
♪ Who are willing to bear
And suffer with me ♪
♪ When I was on earth
And in a cold prison ♪
MARY (VO): A two-year journey
traveling hundreds of miles,
suffering indescribable
hardships and persecution.
♪ I cried to my God ♪
♪ To remember poor me ♪
(ANN GASPING PERCUSSIVELY)
(HORSES WHINNY, NEIGH)
MAN: Whoa! Whoa!
(HORSE WHINNIES)
JAMES: Ye watched, for ye knew
not which hour we would come.
ANN: It is good to watch.
It is always good to watch.
SHATTUCK: Welcome, Mother.
It is an honor to host you.
I think you
will be delighted to see
how many have accepted
our invitation this night.
(FAINT SINGING)
(HORSES WHINNY)
(CONGREGATION WAILING)
(WAILING)
(ALL WAILING, VOCALIZING)
Good evening!
Make room! Make room!
Move closer!
Seeing that so many have
come to join us this night,
please exercise patience
in passing through to sit in
the presence of our Mother Ann.
Forbearance, I say!
We have founded
six new settlements
in New Lebanon, in New York,
Enfield in Connecticut,
and Hancock, Harvard, Shirley,
and Tyringham in Massachusetts.
And now, at Petersham.
Pardon me.
WILLIAM: There shall be
a place for each of you!
WOMAN: Pardon me.
Excuse me.
Let the children through.
Coming through.
GIRL: Mother?
WOMAN: Mother.
-GIRL: Is that her?
-WOMAN: Is it really you?
ANN: Yes, Child.
Do not be frightened, lassies.
(OVERLAPPING CHATTER)
Oh, dear. It delights me so
to make your acquaintance.
Come nearer to me.
I am your Mother.
Do not be shy.
They must find
themselves befuddled.
Let me explain.
I am your Mother,
and your mother's Mother.
We shall erect edifice
here at Petersham.
I call on you,
Brothers and Sisters,
to aid in this endeavor.
MAN: You shall never build here!
Knock out the lights!
(CRASHING, SCREAMING)
MARY: Surround Mother.
Protect her!
ANN: Stay calm, Children!
MAN: Coming through.
ANN: God is with us!
WILLIAM:
Do not fight back, Brothers!
MAN: Where is she?
WILLIAM: Protect Mother Ann!
MAN: Show us the witch!
ANN: Do not fight back!
MAN: Take the Brother!
ANN: Brother!
MAN: This land is not yours.
You shall never live here.
You shall never build here.
ANN: Mrs. Shattuck,
let me go to Brother William!
Let me go!
Mother! No, wait! Mother!
William!
MAN: There she is! Stop her!
ANN: Oh, William.
MAN: Grab the witch!
You, get down, you dog.
WILLIAM: Do not fight back,
Brothers!
ANN: Mary!
MARY: Mother!
(GRUNTING)
WILLIAM: Mary!
-Hold still. Hold her arms back.
-No!
WILLIAM: Take your filthy hands
off my sister!
ANN: William!
WOMAN: Mary! Mary!
WILLIAM: Stop!
(YELPING, GRUNTING)
No!
WOMAN: Oh, please have mercy.
No! No! No!
ANN: God, please!
Please.
(ANN SCREAMS)
MAN: She is not a she at all!
Her sex must be examined.
Tear off her skirts!
(ANN GRUNTING)
What is she? What is she?
A eunuch, I reckon.
There's no phallus.
Did you cut it off, witch?
I forgive you for your sins,
and I will pray for your souls.
Pray for them, Mary!
Father, forgive them,
for they know not what they do!
She has all the right parts,
but she is not a woman.
Rank, she is. It is.
Whatever you are.
(GUNFIRE IN DISTANCE)
What is that?
(GUNFIRE CONTINUES)
I hear clans gathering,
coming in numbers
and carrying rifles.
MAN: Come now. Leave her.
Make haste.
No!
(ANN SCREAMS)
Brother! Wake up.
Brother James!
No!
William. Brother James.
Wake up!
My God.
Mary!
Mary! No!
No!
God!
(BREATHES SHAKILY)
Rest, William.
♪ Down to the deep ♪
♪ And rolling river of Jordan ♪
♪ I will go ♪
♪ I will be baptized again ♪
♪ I will not stand alone ♪
♪ Gospel parents,
Can you bless me? ♪
♪ Will you breathe for me
One prayer? ♪
♪ Holy angels
Guide my spirit ♪
♪ Keep me ever in thy care ♪
Mother.
(BIRDS CHIRPING)
MARY: Mother.
Sister Mary.
How beautiful this tree is now.
Hm?
But some of the apples
will soon fall off.
Some of them
will hold on longer.
Some of them will hold on
till they are half grown
and then fall off.
Some will get ripe.
And so it is with souls
who set out in the way of God.
Many will set out very fair,
and then soon fall away.
Some will go further,
and then fall off.
And some will go further still,
and then fall.
And some will go through.
Mother, I have
the most wonderful news.
General Cornwallis
was surrounded
and forced to surrender
the British position at Yorktown
to the American,
George Washington.
It's perhaps occurred
a long while ago,
but news has
reached us only now.
See, this is why the seasons
have been so peaceful
here at Niskayuna.
Oh, thanks be to God.
All tyrannical
and oppressive governments
shall be overthrown
and destroyed.
And mankind enjoy just
and equal rights
in all matters civil
and religious.
Let me help you back
to your chair.
-Sister.
-Hm?
You must take great care
of God's earth.
Cultivate the land,
yield her increase,
develop her beauty.
This must be done
in the spirit of God.
The earth yields most
to those who love it.
Yes, Mother.
(MARY SIGHS)
Sister, has Brother William
settled in?
He's not come yet today
to visit me.
Brother William departed
this earth last winter, Mother.
Ah yes,
that's right.
Sister, I was
confounded because...
just moments ago...
I saw my Brother William
coming in on a glorious chariot
to take me home.
MARY (VO): At the age of 48,
Ann Lee was at last reunited
with her four earthly children.
♪ O the beautiful treasures ♪
♪ Laid up for the wise ♪
♪ How precious the values ♪
♪ How glorious the prize ♪
♪ Far brighter than diamonds ♪
♪ On princes' brow ♪
♪ And richer than royalty ♪
♪ Can bestow ♪
(ALL VOCALIZING)
(VOCALIZING CONTINUES)
♪ O the beautiful treasures ♪
♪ Laid up for the wise ♪
♪ How precious the values ♪
♪ How glorious the prize ♪
♪ Far brighter than diamonds ♪
♪ On princes' brow ♪
♪ And richer than royalty ♪
♪ Can bestow ♪
♪ It's the
Beautiful treasures ♪
♪ Beautiful treasures ♪
♪ Far brighter than diamonds ♪
♪ On princes' brow ♪
♪ And richer than royalty ♪
♪ Can bestow ♪
♪ Far brighter than diamonds ♪
♪ On princes' brow ♪
♪ And richer than royalty ♪
♪ Can bestow ♪
(FOOTSTEPS APPROACHING)
(BIRDS CHIRPING IN DISTANCE)
A place for everything
and everything in its place.
(BIRDS CHIRPING)
(CREAKING)
(CHIMES RINGING SOFTLY)
(CHIMES CONTINUE RINGING)
(GUITAR PLAYS)
DANIEL BLUMBERG:
♪ Sing the song ♪
♪ Of our revelation ♪
BLUMBERG AND AMANDA SEYFRIED:
♪ Save me far away ♪
♪ Find a tone
And a mother's home ♪
♪ I'm taking off today ♪
♪ Sing the song
Of our own salvation ♪
♪ Mary rings the bell ♪
♪ You and I are
Our own elation ♪
♪ The story has to tell ♪
♪ And I have
My brother's love ♪
♪ And for me,
That's but enough ♪
♪ And the footsteps
On the floor ♪
♪ We can dance forevermore ♪
♪ I'm a woman clothed ♪
♪ I'm a woman ♪
♪ Clothed ♪
♪ I'm a woman clothed
By the sun ♪
♪ All the sinning
And old temptations ♪
♪ Carried us astray ♪
♪ Love is cruel
And yeah, I was fooled ♪
♪ I shake it all away ♪
♪ And I have
My brother's love ♪
♪ And for me
That's but enough ♪
♪ And the footsteps
On the floor ♪
♪ We can dance forevermore ♪
♪ I'm a woman clothed ♪
♪ By the sun ♪
♪ The moon under my feet ♪
♪ And the stars up above ♪
♪ I'm carried off
By Heaven's beat ♪
♪ Like no one ever was ♪
♪ I'm a woman clothed ♪
♪ I'm a woman clothed
By the sun ♪
♪ Ah, by the sun ♪
SEYFRIED: ♪ By the sun ♪
(CHIMES RINGING SOFTLY)
(CHIMES CONTINUE)